Finding Aid for Elizabeth Hughes Gossett papers, 1907-1990
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Elizabeth Hughes Gossett papers
1907-1990
1924-1981
Gossett, Elizabeth Hughes, 1907-1981.
2009186 Aa 2
Volunteer in local and national community and professional organizations and resident of Bloomfield Hills, Michigan from 1947-1981; records include photographs, correspondence, articles, newspaper clippings, and notes related to Gossett’s personal life and volunteer activities.
2.6 linear feet in 3 boxes
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Donated by Antoinette Gossett Denning (donor no. 10247 ) in 2009 and 2010.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Elizabeth Hughes Gossett was born on August 19, 1907 in the Executive Mansion in Albany, New York while her father, Charles Evans Hughes, was serving as the state's Governor. In 1919, at age 11, Elizabeth developed juvenile diabetes, and, by the age of 14, her health had deteriorated significantly. In 1922, her mother, Antoinette Carter Hughes, contacted Dr. Frederick Banting in Toronto, and young Elizabeth began receiving insulin shots, an experimental treatment at the time. Her health improved so significantly after beginning insulin treatments that she returned to school in 1923, and went on to graduate from Barnard College in 1929.
In 1930, Elizabeth married William T. Gossett, and continued to live in the New York City metropolitan area until 1947 when she and William moved to Bloomfield Hills, Michigan, a suburb of Detroit. They would have three children: Antoinette Carter Gossett, William Thomas Gossett Jr., and Elizabeth Evans Gossett.
During her time in Detroit Gossett became actively involved in many community activities, including the Junior League, the United Nations Detroit Board, the Board of Trustees of the Cranbrook Academy of Art, and as a benefactor of Oakland University. She also served on the Board of Trustees for Barnard College, her alma mater, and as the founder and president of the United States Supreme Court Historical Society from 1972 to 1979. In 1979 she received an honorary Doctor of Laws degree from New York Law School. She also actively supported activities and events that honored her father's contributions to American society as Governor of New York (1907-1910), Justice of the United States Supreme Court (1910-1916), Secretary of State (1921-1925), and Chief Justice of the United States Supreme Court (1930-1941).
Elizabeth Hughes Gossett died on April 21, 1981. The Hughes-Gossett Awards of the United States Supreme Court Historical Society have been named in her honor, and continue to be awarded yearly to the best student paper on the history of the court.
The collection consists of four series: Visual Materials, Personal Life and Education, Volunteer Activities and Honors, and Charles Evans Hughes. The collection's strength lies in its documentation of Gossett's years at Barnard College, her personal friendships, and her volunteer activities in various local and national community and professional organizations (1944-1981).
Subjects:
Barnard College--Alumni and alumnae.Alumni and alumnae.; Barnard College--Students.Students.; Gossett, Elizabeth Hughes, 1908-1981.; Hughes, Charles Evans, 1862-1948.; National Conference of Christians and Jews.; Supreme Court Historical Society.; Volunteers--Michigan.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Charity work--Michigan.; Cologne (Germany); Gossett, Elizabeth Hughes, 1908-1981.; National Conference of Christians and Jews.; Travel--Europe.; War damage--Germany--Cologne.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Visual Materials
  The Visual Materials series documents Gossett's trip to Europe in 1948. Additional folders contain photographs related to her volunteer activities, her receipt of an Honorary Doctor of Laws Degree (1977), Charles Evans Hughes's service on the International Court of Justice at The Hague, and portraits of George Romney and Warren Burger.
  - Europe, 1948
    - Belgium (Box 1)
    - France (Box 1)
    - Germany (includes images of the ruins of post-World War II Cologne) (Box 1)
    - Great Britain, 5 folders (Box 1)
    - The Netherlands (Box 1)
    - Switzerland (Box 1)
  - Fleur Cowles Event, Cranbrook Academy of Art, 1974 (Box 1)
  - Honorary Doctor of Laws, New York Law School, 1979 (Box 1)
  - International Court of Justice, The Hague, Netherlands, undated (Box 1)
  - Michigan Bar Association, Mid-Winter Meeting, 1970 (Box 1)
  - National Conference of Christians and Jews, Charles Evans Hughes Awards Ceremonies, 1965-1974; 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Visit of Pope Paul VI to Detroit, 1966 (Box 1)
  - With Millicent McIntosh, President of Barnard College, 1954 (Box 1)
  - Autographed portraits of George Romney and Warren Burger, undated (Box 1)
- Personal Life and Education
  The Personal Life and Education series contains exams, notes, and papers that Gossett wrote while a student at Barnard College in the 1920s, memorabilia related to her father's service as Governor of New York, Secretary of State, and Chief Justice of the Supreme Court, newspaper clippings, travel documents and itineraries, personal correspondence (including several notes from her father), and several essays and poems that Gossett wrote as a child.
  - Article about diabetes treatments Saturday Night, 1981 (Box 2)
  - Barnard College Exams and Grades, 1926-1929 (Box 2)
  - Barnard College Notes and Drafts, 1928; undated (Box 2)
  - Barnard College Papers, 1924-1930 (Box 2)
  - Condolence File, 1981-1982; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Correspondence
    - 1909-1951 (Box 2)
    - 1952-1990, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Re: Charles Evans Hughes Memorial Book, 1954 (Box 2)
    - Re: Charles Evans Hughes "Notes,", 1973 (Box 2)
    - Re: Charles Evans Hughes "Profiles in Courage" Television Program, 1965 (Box 2)
    - Re: Charles Evans Hughes stamp, 1965; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Memorabilia, 1906-1959 (scattered); 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous, 1921-1974 (Box 2)
    (includes photocopied material from 1907)
  - Newspaper Clippings (Hughes and Gossett families), 1908-1981 (scattered); 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Travel Documents, 1925-1980; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Writings and Drawing, 1922; 1931; undated (Box 2)
- Volunteer Activities and Honors
  Volunteer Activities and Honors, the third series, documents Gossett's involvement in several community, educational, and professional organizations from 1944 to 1981. Materials include correspondence, newspaper clippings, magazine articles, notes, official event programs, and a diary.
  - American Bar Association, Miscellaneous Materials, 1968-1969 (Box 2)
  - American Bar Association, Correspondence, 1968-1974 (Box 2)
  - American Bar Association, Diary, 1967-1969 (Box 2)
  - American Red Cross, 1944-1947 (Box 2)
  - Barnard College Alumni Activities, 1952-1976 (Box 2)
  - Fleur Cowles Event, Cranbrook Academy of Art, 1974; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Honorary Doctor of Laws, New York Law School, 1977-1979 (Box 3)
  - Judicial Fellows Program, 1975-1981 (Box 3)
  - Junior League, 1945-1960 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1961-1978 (Box 3)
  - National Council of Christians and Jews, Pamphlets and Correspondence, 1964-1971 (scattered) (Box 3)
  - Oakland University
    - Correspondence, 1967-1971 (Box 3)
    - Continuing Education, circa 1957 (Box 3)
    - Meadowbrook Ball, 1968 (Box 3)
    - Photographs and Clippings, 1960-1972 (scattered) (Box 3)
  - United Nations, Detroit Board, 1965-1967 (Box 3)
  - United States Supreme Court Historical Society, 1969-1980 (Box 3)
- Charles Evans Hughes
  The Charles Evans Hughes series documents Gossett's involvement in organizations and events dedicated to her father's memory. The series also includes some materials produced by Hughes, including a folder of correspondence from him, and miscellaneous materials, including a photocopy of a letter from Herbert Hoover, dated 1940. The rest of the series contains programs, correspondence, and printed materials related to Gossett's involvement in events and dedications honoring Hughes's life and career.
  - Articles (about Hughes by William and Elizabeth Gossett), 1973 (Box 3)
  - Charles Evans Hughes Award, National Conference of Christians and Jews, 1965-1974; 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Charles Evans Hughes Day, Glen Falls, New York, 1976 (Box 3)
  - Charles Evans Hughes Junior High School, 1949-1962 (Box 3)
  - Charles Evans Hughes Room, Association of the Bar of the City of New York, 1980 (Box 3)
  - Charles Evans Hughes Memorial Lectures, 1966 (Box 3)
  - Charles Evans Hughes Scholarship, Oakland University, undated (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1925-1927 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous Posthumous Awards and Honors, 1962-1963 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous, 1940-1977; 2 folders (Box 3)
    (includes a photocopy of a letter from Herbert Hoover to Charles Evans Hughes re: FDR and the election of 1940
  - Telegrams re: Insurance Hall of Fame Induction Ceremony, 1958 (Box 3)
Related Material
Letters from Gossett to her mother, written in 1922 while she was receiving insulin treatments from Dr. Frederick Banting in Toronto, are housed at the University of Toronto's Thomas Fisher Rare Book Library.